<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-03-19T21:01:04+01:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>This is the personal webpage from Sergi Arfelis Espinosa. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">LCA Methodology and Indicators</title><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2023/lca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LCA Methodology and Indicators"/><published>2023-02-21T09:40:16+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-21T09:40:16+01:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2023/lca</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2023/lca/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="lca-methodology">LCA Methodology</h2> <p>LCA is a way to see how a product affects the environment from start to finish, including making it, moving it around, using it, and throwing it away. It looks at how much energy and materials it takes to make something and how it affects the air, water, and soil. It gives us a big picture of how good or bad something is for the environment.</p> <p>It is standardized by ISO 14040 and 14044.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/lca1.png" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> This is the scheme how LCA is described in the ISO </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p>LCA is an iterative process. This means you have to look at your goals and plans in each step of the way; if the data obtained in the inventory are not sufficient or if the results of the impact assessment indicate that the objectives cannot be achieved. they should be reconsidered accordingly.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Goal and scope definition</strong></p> <p>The first step in the LCA assessment is crucial, as it involves defining the objectives, target audience and rationale for the study. This is essential in order to make informed decisions about how to research the product or service under consideration.</p> <p>During this step, it is important to have a clear understanding of what is being analysed, for how long and where. The boundaries of the system under study should be clearly defined, including conceptual, geographical and temporal limits. The quality of the data and the types of information sought should also be established, such as the assumptions made, the impact categories chosen, the allocation rules and the limitations of the study.</p> <p>Finally, it is important to determine the functional unit of the product or service being evaluated or compared. This unit should relate to the quantity of product required to perform a given function rather than simply being expressed in terms of quantity of product. By taking all these factors into account, informed decisions can be made on how to proceed with the LCA study.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Inventory analysis</strong></p> <p>The second step in LCA is where you start collecting data about the thing you’re studying. You gotta figure out how much stuff is going in and coming out of the thing you’re looking at (compilation and quantification of inputs and outputs), and make sure it’s all measured in the same way.</p> <ul> <li>Consumption of materials</li> <li>Energy resources</li> <li>Emissions to water, air, and soil</li> <li>Products</li> </ul> <p>To make it easier, you divide the thing you’re looking at into smaller parts or subsystems and see how much stuff is going in and coming out of each part. Then you group all the data together in a big table (Life Cycle Inventory) so you can look at it all at once.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/lca2.png" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> This is the scheme how the Life Cycle Inventory is described in the ISO </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p>In this phase of LCA, inputs and outputs of the product or service under study are quantified and compiled, and then referred to the functional unit selected in the previous phase. However, it can get complicated when there are co-products produced by the system. In such cases, ISO standards recommend avoiding allocation when possible by including all co-products in the scope of the study, or using system expansion by finding an independent process that produces one of the co-products not related to the system under study. If neither option is feasible, allocation using properties such as mass, energy content, or economic value is recommended.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Impact assessment</strong></p> <p>Life Cycle Impact Assessment (LCIA) is about understanding the environmental impact of the data collected in the inventory phase. It simplifies the data by turning it into a few impact category indicators like global warming, acidification, ozone layer depletion, or ecotoxicity.</p> <p>LCIA typically involves several steps, including:</p> <ul> <li>Classification: This simply means sorting the inventory flows or substances according to the impact categories they contribute to.</li> <li>Characterization: This step consists of quantifying the contribution of the substances classified in each impact category. expressed in a common unit. This is done by using “characterization factors”; factors that show the relative contribution of one singular emission at a given impact category using a reference unit.</li> <li>Normalization: This step involves comparing the results of the previous steps to reference values, which provides a perspective on the relative significance of the results.</li> <li>Grouping: This step involves combining the results of the previous steps into a smaller number of indicator scores (such as global/regional/local impacts or impacts with high/medium/low priority).</li> <li>Weighting: This step consists of converting the environmental profile to a single impact score. by means of using “weighting factors” based on subjective value judgments. The advantage of doing so is that the different impact categories (measured in different units) are transformed into a numerical score of environmental impact, thus facilitating decision-making. At the same time, the biggest drawback is that those weighting factors are mainly based on political criteria with hardly any scientific basis. Moreover, a lot of information is lost, and reality is oversimplified.</li> </ul> <p>The first two steps (classification and characterization) are mandatory in LCA according to ISO standards, whereas the last three steps (normalization, grouping, and weighting) are optional and can be adapted to the specific needs of the study.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Interpretation</strong></p> <p>This is the last phase of an LCA (although. as explained above. it runs in parallel with the others). Here. the results obtained in the inventory and in the impact assessment are interpreted. while considering the defined goal and the limitations defined by the scope of the study. and recommendations for reducing the environmental impact of the analyzed system are formulated. Interpretation involves a review of all the previous phases of the analysis. in order to assess the consistency of the assumptions taken and the data quality. In the interpretation of the results. techniques such as sensitivity analysis. assessment of the limitations of the study and an external review must also be taken into account.</p> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="environmental-impact-categories">Environmental Impact Categories</h2> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Acidification</strong></p> <p>Acidifying substances such as sulphur dioxide (SO2) and nitrogen oxides (NOx), predominantly emitted through fossil fuel combustion, can remain in the atmosphere for a few days and be transported over great distances. When converted chemically into acids (sulphuric and nitric), they deposit into the soil and surface water, leading to changes in their chemical composition. This can harm ecosystems and cause acidification, as evidenced by the <a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/forest-dynamics-in-europe-and">decline of forests in Central and Eastern Europe</a>, and the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jglr.2020.05.006">proliferation of ‘dead’ lakes in Scandinavia and Canada</a>. Acidification is quantified in terms of mole of H+ eq as an impact category in LCA.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/lca3.png" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Scheme of acidification process </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Cancer human health effects</strong></p> <p>Cancer is a disease that results from genetic mutations that disrupt normal cell functions. Some of these mutations happen naturally during the replication of DNA when cells divide, but others occur due to exposure to environmental factors that damage DNA. These environmental factors can include various substances, like the chemicals found in tobacco smoke, or radiation, such as the ultraviolet rays in sunlight. In LCA, the impact category for cancer is typically measured in Comparative Toxic Units for humans (CTUh).</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Climate Change</strong></p> <p>Climate change is an impact category that focuses on the global warming caused by human-induced greenhouse gas emissions. The majority of these emissions come from the burning of fossil fuels for energy consumption, as well as from agriculture, deforestation, and industrial processes. Carbon dioxide (CO2) and methane (CH4) are the primary greenhouse gases, accounting for more than 90% of emissions. Climate change leads to various consequences, including rising temperatures, more frequent droughts and wildfires, changing rainfall patterns, and melting of glaciers and snow. Another impact of climate change is the rising of the global mean sea level. This impact category is typically measured in Global Warming Potential (GWP) or Carbon Footprint.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/lca4.png" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Scheme of climate change process </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p>This impact category is measured in kg of carbon dioxide equivalents.</p> <p>Climate change fossil is referred to the part of climate change that is caused by the use and combustion of fossil fuels. Thus, greenhouse gas emissions from biogenic sources (such as wood. paper or cardboard production) are not considered.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Ecotoxicity freshwater</strong></p> <p>Ecotoxicity freshwater refers to the impact on fresh water ecosystems, as a result of emissions of toxic substances to air, water and soil. Ecotoxicity Potential is calculated taking into account fate, exposure and effects of toxic substances. The time horizon is infinite. This impact category is measured in Comparative Toxic Unit for ecosystems (CTUe).</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Eutrophication (terrestrial. freshwater and marine)</strong></p> <p>The overloading of seas. lakes. rivers and streams with nutrients (nitrogen and phosphorus) can result in a series of adverse effects known as eutrophication. Phosphorus is the key nutrient for eutrophication in fresh waters and nitrate is the key substance for salt waters.</p> <p>In severe cases of eutrophication. massive blooms of algae (sessile and planktonic) occur. Some blooms are toxic. As dead algae decompose. the oxygen in the water is used up; bottom-dwelling animals die and fish either die or leave the affected area. Increased nutrient concentrations can also lead to changes in the aquatic vegetation. The unbalanced ecosystem and changed chemical composition make the water body unsuitable for recreational and other uses. and the water becomes unacceptable for human consumption. High concentrations of nitrate in drinking water are considered a human-health problem because in the stomach nitrate is converted rapidly to nitrite. which can cause a reduction in the blood’s oxygen-carrying capacity.</p> <p>The main source of nitrogen pollution is run-off from agricultural land. whereas most phosphorus pollution comes from households and industry. The rapid increase in industrial production and household consumption during the 20th century has resulted in greater volumes of nutrient-rich wastewater. Nutrient removal during wastewater treatment in sewage-treatment plants is vital to minimise the impact of nitrogen and phosphorus pollution on Europe’s water bodies.</p> <p>This impact category is measured in fraction of nutrients reaching freshwater end compartment (P) [kg P eq.] for eutrophication freshwater; in fraction of nutrients reaching marine end compartment (N) [kg N eq.] for eutrophication marine; and in accumulated exceedance [mole of N eq.] for eutrophication terrestrial</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Ionizing radiation, human health</strong></p> <p>This impact category is referred to the damage on human health related to the routine releases of radioactive material to the environment. It takes into account fate and exposure. This impact category is measured in a Human Health effect model and expressed in kg of uranium 235 equivalents released to the air [kg U235 eq. to air].</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Land Use</strong></p> <p>There are different models and approaches to evaluate the effects on land use due to human intervention. Although none of them has been completely agreed by the scientific community, this impact category is usually measured using a soil quality index (biotic production, erosion resistance and mechanical filtration) based on soil organic matter content and expressed in points [Pt].</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Human toxicity, non-cancer</strong></p> <p>Non-cancer human health effects refer to the risks associated with exposure to various substances through different means (oral, dermal, or inhalation) that are not related to cancer. The impact category assesses the effects based on the minimum risk level, reference dose, and reference concentration that estimate the doses and exposures unlikely to cause non-carcinogenic health effects. Reference concentrations apply to potential non-cancer effects from inhalation. The impact is measured in Comparative Toxic Unit for humans (CTUh).</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Ozone depletion</strong></p> <p>Ozone depletion includes two related events that have occurred since the late 1970s: a gradual decrease of around four percent in the total amount of ozone in the Earth’s atmosphere (the ozone layer), and a much larger springtime decline in stratospheric ozone around the polar region, known as the ozone hole. In addition to these stratospheric events, there are also springtime polar tropospheric ozone depletion events. The primary cause of ozone depletion and the ozone hole is human-made chemicals, including refrigerants, solvents, and propellants, all referred to as ozone-depleting substances (ODS). These substances are transported into the stratosphere and catalyze the breakdown of ozone into oxygen. The impact category is measured in ozone depletion potential and expressed in kg CFC-11 eq.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/lca5.png" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Scheme of ozone depletion process </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Photochemical ozone formation, human health</strong></p> <p>Ozone is formed in the troposphere under the influence of sunlight when nitrogen oxides are present. When organic volatile compounds (VOC’s) are also present, peroxy radicals can be produced. Peroxy radicals are highly reactive and toxic compounds, and the presence of peroxy radicals can result in an increase of the concentration of ozone through a complex reaction pattern. Ozone is a secondary pollutant. as there is practically no ozone present in source emissions derived from human activity.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/lca6.png" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Scheme of photochemical ozone formation process </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p>Tropospheric ozone, also known as ground-level ozone, is a significant environmental threat on a regional scale. It is harmful to human health at high concentrations and can cause damage to vegetation even at lower concentrations. Ozone is a transboundary pollutant that can be produced or consumed by other pollutants during long-range transport. The health impacts of ozone have traditionally been attributed to high peaks in ozone concentration, known as ozone episodes. The impact category is measured in tropospheric ozone concentration increase and expressed in non-methane volatile organic compounds equivalents (kg NMVOC eq).</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Resource use, fossils</strong></p> <p>This indicator evaluates the use of resources with energy carriers from fossil fuels, using reserve base as reference for resources stock. This impact category is measured in abiotic resource depletion-fossil fuels (ADP-fossil) and expressed in MJ.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Resource use, minerals and metals</strong></p> <p>This indicator evaluates the use of mineral and metal resources. using reserve base as reference for resources stock. This impact category is measured in abiotic resource depletion (ADP-ultimate reserves) and expressed in kg of antimony equivalents [kg Sb eq.].</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Particulate matter</strong></p> <p>This indicator evaluates the effects on human disease (chronic long term mortality and chronic bronchitis) due to the inhalation of fine particulate matter. below 2.5 μm. There are different models and methods to estimate this effect. all of them based on exposure and fate. This impact category is measured in disease incidence.</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>Water use</strong></p> <p>Water scarcity is a pressing issue as demand is outpacing supply, with estimates suggesting a potential shortage of over 40% by 2030 if no action is taken. Increased human water use has doubled in the past 50 years, leading to low flows in various regions and threats to freshwater availability due to population growth, demand for food, and climate change. Global food demand for 2050 could intensify water stress, posing risks to both human water security and ecosystems. Approximately half of the world’s major river basins experience water scarcity, with restrictions projected to increase due to climate change. The water use indicator assesses potential scarcity and is measured in scarcity-adjusted water use expressed in m3 world eq.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Learn-post"/><category term="Sustainability"/><category term="LCA"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Brief description of the LCA methodology and the Environmental Impact categories]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Carbon Footprint and Its Importance in Reducing Climate Change</title><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2023/cf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Carbon Footprint and Its Importance in Reducing Climate Change"/><published>2023-01-13T09:40:16+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T09:40:16+01:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2023/cf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2023/cf/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Carbon footprint is the total amount of greenhouse gas emissions caused by an individual, organization, product, or event. ISO 14064 is an internationally recognized standard for carbon footprint management, which provides guidelines for organizations and businesses to measure, report, and reduce their greenhouse gas emissions. The ISO 14064 standard is divided into three parts: Part 1 covers the principles and requirements for the organization’s carbon footprint management, Part 2 is for the quantification, monitoring, and reporting of the product carbon footprint, and Part 3 provides guidelines for validating and verifying greenhouse gas claims.</p> <h2 id="climate-change">Climate change</h2> <p>Climate change is a pressing global issue caused by the increase in greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, primarily carbon dioxide. The burning of fossil fuels, deforestation, and other human activities are major sources of greenhouse gas emissions. The consequences of climate change are severe, such as rising sea levels, more frequent natural disasters, and loss of biodiversity. To mitigate the effects of climate change, it is essential to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and adopt sustainable practices in all areas of life.</p> <h2 id="product-carbon-footprint">Product Carbon Footprint</h2> <p>A product’s carbon footprint is the total amount of greenhouse gas emissions caused by the product throughout its life cycle, from the extraction of raw materials to the product’s disposal. Measuring the carbon footprint of a product can help companies identify areas where they can reduce emissions, such as using recycled materials, improving the energy efficiency of production processes, and optimizing transportation. The ISO 14064 standard provides guidelines for measuring and reporting the carbon footprint of a product, which can help companies make informed decisions and communicate their environmental impact to consumers.</p> <p>The formula to calculate carbon footprint varies depending on the source of emissions being considered. Generally, the formula involves multiplying the amount of greenhouse gas emissions generated by a particular activity or source, by the relevant global warming potential (GWP) factor, which represents the amount of warming caused by that gas over a certain period of time.</p> <p>For example, to calculate the carbon footprint of an individual’s car travel, you would need to know the amount of fuel consumed and the corresponding emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases, such as methane and nitrous oxide. The total amount of greenhouse gas emissions would be multiplied by the relevant GWP factors for each gas to determine the carbon footprint.</p> <p>Different calculators and methodologies use different assumptions and factors, so the exact formula used may vary. The ISO 14064 standard provides guidelines for calculating carbon footprint, including the use of standardized factors for greenhouse gases and the consideration of emissions from the entire life cycle of a product or service.</p> <h2 id="organisation-carbon-footprint">Organisation Carbon Footprint</h2> <p>Organisations can calculate their carbon footprint by identifying all their sources of emissions, such as electricity consumption, transportation, and waste. Once an organization has identified its sources of emissions, it can implement measures to reduce its carbon footprint, such as using renewable energy, energy-efficient technologies, and reducing travel. The ISO 14064 standard provides guidance on how to reduce emissions and encourages organizations to establish a carbon reduction target and report their progress.</p> <p>The <a href="https://ghgprotocol.org/">GHG Protocol</a> is a widely recognized standard for measuring and managing greenhouse gas emissions. The protocol defines three scopes of emissions, which are:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Scope 1 emissions</strong>: These are direct emissions from sources that are owned or controlled by the organization. Examples of scope 1 emissions include emissions from combustion of fuels in boilers or vehicles, or emissions from on-site waste disposal.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Scope 2 emissions</strong>: These are indirect emissions from the consumption of purchased electricity, heat, or steam. Scope 2 emissions result from the production of the purchased energy and are associated with the organization’s activities.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Scope 3 emissions</strong>: These are all other indirect emissions that occur in the organization’s value chain, including emissions from suppliers, customers, and transportation. Scope 3 emissions are often the largest source of greenhouse gas emissions for many organizations and are the most challenging to quantify and manage.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Scope 1 and 2 emissions are considered to be under the direct control of an organization, while scope 3 emissions are often outside the direct control of an organization. Nevertheless, organizations have a responsibility to account for and manage scope 3 emissions to address their full impact on the environment.</p> <p>The GHG Protocol provides guidance for measuring and reporting greenhouse gas emissions across all three scopes. This enables organizations to identify their most significant sources of emissions and take actions to reduce their carbon footprint, by setting reduction targets and implementing measures to improve efficiency and reduce waste throughout their value chain.</p> <p>By measuring and managing their greenhouse gas emissions across all three scopes, organizations can demonstrate their commitment to addressing climate change and contribute to a more sustainable future.</p> <h2 id="reducing-carbon-footprint">Reducing Carbon Footprint</h2> <p>Reducing your carbon footprint is essential to mitigate climate change. Simple measures such as using public transport, reducing meat consumption, and turning off electronics when not in use can make a significant difference. Individuals can also make a difference by using renewable energy, recycling, and reducing waste. Organizations can take steps to reduce their carbon footprint by implementing energy-efficient technologies, using renewable energy sources, and investing in green infrastructure.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>The carbon footprint is an important measure of the impact of human activities on the environment. The ISO 14064 standard provides guidelines for organizations and businesses to measure, report, and reduce their greenhouse gas emissions. Reducing our carbon footprint is essential to mitigate climate change, and simple measures can make a significant difference. By implementing sustainable practices, individuals and organizations can reduce their carbon footprint and contribute to a healthier planet.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Learn-post"/><category term="Sustainability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Climate Change, Organisation and Product Carbon footprint and others]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COP27 - How events unfolded and comparison with previous editions</title><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2022/cop27/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COP27 - How events unfolded and comparison with previous editions"/><published>2022-11-22T09:40:16+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-22T09:40:16+01:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2022/cop27</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2022/cop27/"><![CDATA[<p>I have recently arrived from Sharm el Sheikh, Egypt, where <a href="https://cop27.eg/#/">COP27</a> was held. I assisted the conference as an observer from the <a href="https://www.esci.upf.edu/en/unesco-chair-in-life-cycle-and-climate-change/catedra-introduction">UNESCO Chair in Life Cycle and Climate Change ESCI-UPF</a>.</p> <p>This COP marks 30 years since the <a href="https://unfccc.int/">United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC)</a> was adopted and seven years since the Paris Agreement was agreed upon at COP21. We arrived at COP27 with an anomalous situation compared to previous years. The war between Russia and Ukraine affects the rest of the countries and is monopolizing governments’ priorities and budgets. While taking action is crucial, the uncertainty of the crises suggested that the negotiations would be complicated.</p> <p>Loss and damage and Climate Justice were on the focus of the discussion, global heating consequences are affecting most to those countries that are contributing least to GHG emissions. Funding is essential. It is not a matter of lending money or helping developing countries; it is a matter of accounting for responsibility and following the polluter pays principle.</p> <p>You can check here articles about my thoughts on the results and decisions made in Sharm el-Sheikh.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.esciupfnews.com/2022/11/30/cop27-how-events-unfolded/">COP27: How Events Unfolded</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.esciupfnews.com/2022/11/23/climate-change-dilemma-cop27/">The Climate Change Dilemma</a></li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/14.jfif" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> This is me in my first participation in a COP 🚀 </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <h2 id="how-large-was-the-carbon-footprint-of-cop27-in-sharm-el-sheikh-compared-to-cop25-in-madrid-and-cop26-in-glasgow">How large was the carbon footprint of COP27 in Sharm el-Sheikh compared to COP25 in Madrid and COP26 in Glasgow?</h2> <p>The Conference of Parties (COP) is an annual gathering of world leaders and policymakers to discuss global climate change issues. The 27th edition of COP was held in Sharm el Sheikh, Egypt in 2022. In this blog post, we will discuss the estimated carbon footprint of COP27, based on previous COP events in Glasgow (COP26) and Madrid (COP25). To estimate the carbon footprint of COP27, we analyzed data from COP26 and COP25. The number of participants in each edition has been reported in the press:</p> <ul> <li>COP25 Madrid: 26,700 participants (<a href="https://enb.iisd.org/chile-madrid-climate-change-conference-cop25">source</a>)</li> <li>COP26 Glasgow: 40,000 participants (<a href="https://www.un.org/en/climatechange/cop26#:~:text=The%20UN%20Climate%20Change%20Conference,observers%20and%203.886%20media%20representatives">source</a>)</li> <li>COP27 Sharm el-Sheikh: 35,000 participants (<a href="https://www.un.org/en/climatechange/cop27#:~:text=From%206%20to%2020%20November%2C%20COP27%20held%20high%2Dlevel%20and,world%20and%20across%20different%20sectors">source</a>)</li> </ul> <p>The total of tons of CO2 equivalent emissions in COP25 and COP26, being <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/11/12/cop26-climate-summit-record-co2-emissions-air-travel-main-culprit.html">51,101.00</a> and <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/11/12/cop26-climate-summit-record-co2-emissions-air-travel-main-culprit.html">102,500.00</a> respectively.</p> <p>The main emission sources in all the cases are flights and accommodations of participants, as reported in the calculation of the carbon footprint in COP26 Glasgow. The same share between flights (60%) and accommodation (40%) in the carbon footprint is being assumed in COP25, COP26, and COP27. In the case of COP27, where total carbon footprint is not available, it has been calculated from the total value in COP26 as directly proportional to the number of participants in each event.</p> <p>Even though, due to airport capacity, I suspect even more flights are needed to get Sharm than Glasgow (most flights to COP27 had a stopover in Cairo). In addition, carbon footprint values in accommodation has been recalculated with a <a href="https://www.aceee.org/international-scorecard">correcting factor corresponding to the energy efficiency of each country</a>.</p> <ul> <li>Spanish correcting factor according to energy efficiency: 0.660</li> <li>British correcting factor according to energy efficiency: 0.725</li> <li>Egyptian correcting factor according to energy efficiency: 0.315</li> </ul> <p><br/></p> <p>The following table discloses the results estimated in each COP edition:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th></th> <th>COP25</th> <th>COP26</th> <th>COP27</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Total (tons of CO2)</td> <td>75,698.48</td> <td>102,500.00</td> <td>148,177.58</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Flights (tons of CO2)</td> <td>30,660.60</td> <td>61,500.00</td> <td>53,812.50</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Accommodation (tons of CO2)</td> <td>45,037.88</td> <td>41,000.00</td> <td>94,365.08</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <style>table{border-collapse:collapse;width:100%;color:#333}th,td{border:1px solid #ddd;padding:8px;text-align:left}th{background-color:#ccbcbc}tr:hover{background-color:#b9d1ae}</style> <p><br/></p> <p>Results per number of participants is presented in next table:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th></th> <th>COP25</th> <th>COP26</th> <th>COP27</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Total (tons of CO2)</td> <td>2.84</td> <td>2.56</td> <td>4.23</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Flights (tons of CO2)</td> <td>1.15</td> <td>1.54</td> <td>1.54</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Accommodation (tons of CO2)</td> <td>1.69</td> <td>1.03</td> <td>2.70</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <style>table{border-collapse:collapse;width:100%;color:#333}th,td{border:1px solid #ddd;padding:8px;text-align:left}th{background-color:#ccbcbc}tr:hover{background-color:#b9d1ae}</style> <p><br/></p> <p>In conclusion, the estimated carbon footprint of COP27 in Sharm el-Sheikh is significant and apparently much higher than previous editions, but steps can be taken to reduce emissions in future COP events. This can include using virtual conferencing technology to reduce air travel and promoting sustainable practices such as using renewable energy sources and reducing waste in accommodations. As the world comes together to address the urgent issue of climate change, it’s important for us to lead by example and take concrete steps to reduce our carbon footprint.</p> <p><strong>Note</strong>: The results reported for COP27 are based on calculations of previous editions and estimates.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info-post"/><category term="Learn-post"/><category term="Sustainability"/><category term="COP"/><category term="Event"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out my experience in my first COP! Find here a comparison on the carbon footprint of COP27 with previous editions (COP26 and COP25)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CuidaPro. Healthcare for old people living in rural areas</title><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2022/cuidapro_release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CuidaPro. Healthcare for old people living in rural areas"/><published>2022-10-25T10:40:16+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-25T10:40:16+02:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2022/cuidapro_release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2022/cuidapro_release/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Rural areas around the world are experiencing an unprecedented demographic shift, where depopulation and ageing are posing new challenges for healthcare providers. The combination of a decline in birth rates and an increase in life expectancy has resulted in a rapidly ageing rural population. This demographic shift is causing significant social and economic changes, with significant impacts on healthcare systems. In this context, the healthcare of elderly individuals is an urgent concern, and new approaches are needed to address the unique needs of the elderly population in rural areas.</p> <h2 id="loneliness-and-isolation">Loneliness and Isolation</h2> <p>Elderly individuals living in rural areas face a unique set of challenges. As young people move to urban areas for work and better opportunities, the elderly are left behind. This situation can lead to loneliness and social isolation, which can have a negative impact on physical and mental health. Furthermore, the lack of access to healthcare providers in rural areas can make it difficult for elderly individuals to receive the medical attention they need.</p> <h2 id="the-role-of-technology">The Role of Technology</h2> <p>New technologies can play an essential role in addressing the healthcare needs of elderly individuals living in rural areas. Telemedicine, for example, can provide access to medical professionals regardless of location. Remote monitoring technologies can also help healthcare providers keep track of elderly individuals’ vital signs, ensuring timely intervention in the event of a medical emergency. These technologies can help address the isolation and lack of access to healthcare services that elderly individuals often experience in rural areas.</p> <h2 id="community-based-care">Community-Based care</h2> <p>Community-based care is another approach that can be effective in addressing the healthcare needs of elderly individuals in rural areas. Community-based care programs are designed to bring healthcare services closer to the community, making it easier for elderly individuals to access medical attention. These programs can also provide socialization opportunities, reducing loneliness and social isolation. By bringing healthcare services and socialization opportunities closer to the community, community-based care programs can help address some of the unique challenges faced by elderly individuals in rural areas.</p> <h2 id="cuidapro">CuidaPro</h2> <p><a href="https://www.cuida-pro.com">CuidaPro</a> has arrived to revolutionize the elderly sector and respond to their needs and those of their families.</p> <p>On behalf of the entire team, we would like to express our sincere gratitude to Mr. Enric Adell Moragrega, vice-president of the Provincial Council of Tarragona and Mr. Felip Monclús, director of the Territorial Services of Social Rights Terres de l’Ebre for his assistance, participation and words. It was a pleasure to have you. To thank Leonor Bertomeu from Delta.cat for her great work as presenter and facilitator of the event. We would also like to thank the political representatives of the Council of Els Muntells, Sant Jaume d’Enveja, Amposta, Poble Nou del Delta and Tortosa for their assistance. Thanks to the Vice Dean of Lands of the Ebre of the Official College of Social Work of Catalonia. Thanks to the musicians Laia and Marc from the Tortosa Music Conservatory for their excellent performance and to Conficon Hostesses for their professionalism. Of course, to the Chamber of Commerce of Tortosa for its great involvement attention. And last, but not least, thank you for the presence and support of the group of care workers who are part of the labor exchange and who were by our side. You are CuidaPro’s reason for being.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/cuidapro1.jfif" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/cuidapro2.jfif" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Inauguration ceremony of CuidaPro </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style> <p>CuidaPro has a dynamic, changing and always open job board. We are looking for the best professionals who want to dedicate themselves to the care of people in Tarragona. Whether you are interested in working full-time, half-time, part-time, or you prefer to work as an internal staff, we want to get to know you.</p> <p>You can send your CV to <a href="mailto:personal@cuida-pro.com">personal@cuida-pro.com</a> or fill out the following <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfej1xNtQNuGPaDnO8j4vuEMpMDWyfKJuYNQysQH4G9PcLWbA/viewform">form</a>.</p> <p>If you know someone who might be interested, please share!</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>The healthcare of elderly individuals living in rural areas is an urgent concern that requires innovative solutions. The demographic shift towards ageing and depopulation in rural areas requires new approaches to address the unique challenges faced by this population. Technology and community-based care are two approaches that can be effective in providing access to healthcare services and reducing social isolation. As healthcare providers and policymakers work to address these challenges, it is crucial to recognize the importance of elderly individuals’ healthcare needs in rural areas and ensure that they receive the attention and support they need.</p> <p>CuidaPro was present at the event of the 8th delivery of the SuperCuidadores Awards organized by SUPERCUIDADORES with the support of UNIR - La Universidad en Internet. Counting on the honorary presidency of the Kings of Spain and the presence of the president of the Community of Madrid, Mrs. Isabel Díaz Ayuso. We spent a unique day accompanied by representatives of the socio-health sector and care for the dependent. The event took place at the emblematic Real Casa de Correos in Madrid’s Puerta del Sol.</p> <p>The main objective was to give visibility to the group of carers and the great work they carry out on a daily basis. We went back to home with one sentence: “Take care as you would like to be taken care of”. We will continue to select, accompany, train and support all the professionals in our team so that this is the reason for BEING and the reason for DOING 🧡.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/sc1.jfif" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/sc2.jfif" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/sc3.jfif" class="custom-image-class rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> SUPERCUIDADORES Awards </div> <style>.custom-image-class{max-width:100%;height:auto;max-height:600px}</style>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info-post"/><category term="CuidaPro"/><category term="Entrepreneurship"/><category term="Elderly"/><category term="Healthcare"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We inaugurated CuidaPro in "Cambra de Comerç de Tortosa"]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Doing a PhD in Life Cycle Assessment for Green Chemistry processes</title><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2021/Doing_PhD_grenchemLCA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doing a PhD in Life Cycle Assessment for Green Chemistry processes"/><published>2021-06-01T10:40:16+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T10:40:16+02:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2021/Doing_PhD_grenchemLCA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2021/Doing_PhD_grenchemLCA/"><![CDATA[<p>Switching jobs can be a daunting task, especially if you’ve spent years in the same industry. However, sometimes the risk is worth taking if it leads to a fulfilling and rewarding career. This is exactly what happened to me when I left my previous job as a Plant Engineer in the private industry to pursue a PhD in Life Cycle Assessment for green chemistry processes.</p> <p>Making the switch wasn’t easy, but it was definitely worth it. As a Plant Engineer for the <a href="https://es.dow.com/es-es/public-report/tarragona-turnaround.html">Dow Chemical TurnAround in Tarragona 2021</a>, I was responsible for ensuring that all the planned tasks were efficient and cost-effective. While the work was challenging, I found myself wanting to do more to help the environment. This desire led me to explore the field of green chemistry, which focuses on developing chemical products and processes that are environmentally sustainable.</p> <p>When I started my PhD in Life Cycle Assessment for green chemistry processes, I knew that I had made the right decision. My PhD is a collaborative project between <a href="https://www.esci.upf.edu/en/unesco-chair-in-life-cycle-and-climate-change/catedra-introduction">UNESCO Chair in Life Cycle and Climate Change ESCI-UPF</a> and the Swiss company, <a href="https://deasyl.com/">Deasyl SA</a>. The work is fascinating, and I’m learning new things every day. I’m working on projects that have real-world applications, and I know that the work I’m doing will have a positive impact on the environment.</p> <p>While salary or resources might not be as abundant as in a multinational private company, one of the things that I love about my new job is the collaborative environment. I’m working with a team of people who are passionate about green chemistry and sustainability and who are all working towards the same goal. We share ideas and work together to find solutions to complex problems. Here, we not only know what and how we do things… but we also know why we do those things.</p> <p>Another thing that I appreciate about my new job is the flexibility. As a Plant Engineer, I was always on call and had tighter schedule. Now, although the workload is still high, I have more control over my working hours, which allows me to spend more time with my family and pursue other interests outside of work.</p> <p>Overall, I’m so happy that I made the switch to a career in green chemistry research. I feel like I’m making a difference and contributing to a better future for all of us. If you’re considering a career change, my advice is to follow your passion and take the leap. It may be scary at first, but it could lead to a more fulfilling and rewarding career in the long run.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Info-post"/><category term="Chemistry"/><category term="LCA"/><category term="Engineering"/><category term="Research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[switching jobs from private industry to academia]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using IoT to Plastics Management</title><link href="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2021/IoT4Plastics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using IoT to Plastics Management"/><published>2021-05-22T23:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-22T23:01:00+02:00</updated><id>https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2021/IoT4Plastics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sergiarfelis.com/blog/2021/IoT4Plastics/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Plastics are one of the most widely used materials in the world today. They are versatile, durable, and inexpensive, making them popular in a wide range of industries. The global plastic market is expected to reach USD 722.6 billion by 2027, with an annual growth rate of 3.4%. This growth is attributed to the increasing demand for plastic products in various applications such as packaging, construction, automotive, and electronics.</p> <h2 id="advantages-of-plastics">Advantages of plastics</h2> <p>Plastics have many advantages as a material, which is why they have become so prevalent in modern society. One of the most significant advantages is their versatility. Plastics can be molded into any shape or size, making them suitable for a wide range of applications. They are also lightweight, which makes them easy to transport and handle.</p> <p>Plastics are an essential material with many applications at the macro- and micro-economic level. They help to solve a multitude of problems that society has had to face throughout history. They are used as lightweight and innovative materials in the automotive industry, where they help to save fuel and reduce CO2 emissions. They have a high performance when used as insulators, so they contribute to achieve considerable energy savings. They are widely used as packaging, where they ensure food safety and reduce food waste. In recent years, they have even been combined with 3D printing technology for the manufacture of biocompatible medical parts that can save human lives.</p> <p>Another advantage of plastics is their durability. Plastics can withstand extreme temperatures, chemicals, and weather conditions, making them suitable for use in harsh environments. They are also resistant to impact, which makes them ideal for use in packaging and transportation.</p> <p>Finally, plastics are relatively inexpensive to produce, which makes them an attractive option for manufacturers. This low cost allows for the production of large quantities of products at a low price point.</p> <h2 id="inconvenients-of-plastics">Inconvenients of plastics</h2> <p>Despite the many advantages of plastics, they also have some significant drawbacks. One of the most significant is their potential to release harmful chemicals. Plastics are made from petroleum-based materials, which can contain toxic chemicals such as bisphenol A (BPA) and phthalates. These chemicals can leach into food, water, and other substances, which can have harmful effects on human health. In addition, the production of plastics requires a significant amount of energy and resources, which can contribute to climate change and other environmental problems.</p> <p>But what may be the biggest issue with plastics is related to its waste management. Plastics are not biodegradable, which means they can persist in the environment for hundreds of years. This persistence leads to significant problems such as plastic pollution, which can harm wildlife, ecosystems, and human health. The problems caused by plastic waste and the current situation of the sector make it necessary to rethink processes and business models to ensure the sustainability of the sector. The need to develop a circular economy in the plastics industry and the actions this entails have already been identified in the literature, together with analyses of how these needs might be met through the use of technologies and enablers of Industry 4.0.</p> <p>This recently published <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-030-90033-5_14">article</a> aims the preliminary design of a plastic waste management network that integrates the technologies and concepts of Industry 4.0 and the principles of the circular economy. For this purpose, the Industrial Internet Reference Architecture (IIRA) methodology has been used to cover all stages of the life cycle of plastic products. A model combining the use of Industrial Internet of Things (IIoT) and Artificial Intelligence (AI) technologies to optimize plastic waste management is presented as a sustainable technological and economical alternative with the potential to improve environmental, social and corporate governance for greater sustainability of the plastics industry.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0 text-center"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/9.jfif" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> This is the graphical abstract of the published article described in this post </div> <p>The holistic methodology adopted enables the development of a versatile, adaptable and scalable architecture that will be of interest to public and private actors in the plastics value chain.</p> <p>The article is a result of my final project for the master’s degree in Industry 4.0 at the International University of La Rioja and it has been developed together with the <a href="https://scholar.google.es/citations?user=6OzCWSIAAAAJ&amp;hl=es">Dr. Daniel María González Pérez</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.unir.net/profesores/javier-rainer/">Dr. J. Javier Rainer</a>.</p> <h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2> <p>Plastics have become an integral part of modern society due to their versatility, durability, and low cost. However, their widespread use has also led to significant environmental and health problems. It is essential to reduce the consumption of single-use plastics, promote recycling, and rethink the strategy when using plastic as a material. By doing so, we can reduce the impact of plastics on the environment and create a more sustainable future for generations to come.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="newpaper-post"/><category term="IoT"/><category term="Plastics"/><category term="Engineering"/><category term="Industry4.0"/><category term="Research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Architecture Development to Incorporate Industry 4.0 Solutions to Plastics Management - Circular Economy]]></summary></entry></feed>